<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/BannatyneMS/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/BannatyneMS/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-07-24T09:39:33-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/BannatyneMS/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Bannatyne MS Project</title><subtitle>This website provides information and updates for the ongoing Bannatyne MS project.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Question of W. Tod Ritchie and the 20th Century</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/BannatyneMS/2019/07/19/entry2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Question of W. Tod Ritchie and the 20th Century" /><published>2019-07-19T09:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-07-19T09:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/BannatyneMS/2019/07/19/entry2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/BannatyneMS/2019/07/19/entry2.html">&lt;p&gt;An aspect of this project that has brought some unprecedented, and highly enjoyable, information to light is the role of one W. Tod Ritchie. This name may be familiar for those who have worked with the Bannatyne MS previously, but for those who have not, W. Tod Ritchie was the editor of the full manuscript for the Scottish Text Society in the 1920s and 1930s. In 2017, I had a remarkable encounter in a bookshop in Wigtown, Scotland’s Book Town - I found an edition of William Dunbar’s poetry that I had not previously seen. It was bound in beautiful red, and my magpie tendencies got the better of me. I was astonished to find, upon closer inspection, that this volume was inscribed as having belonged to W. Tod Ritchie himself. It was at this point that I started to really think about the nature of an editor’s relationship with their text. Holding the book in my hands, I could visualise Ritchie reading this volume, considering the choices he would go on to make in his authoritative and exhaustive edition of the Bannatyne, upon which I had so heavily relied throughout my studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came to my own project with a naïvete: I believed that I had selected a challenge which was a project in objectivity, and that my ‘gift’ to scholarship would be an objective edition. Even now, merely months on from beginning the project, I can see the inherent problems with this. A truly objective edition is an impossibility, and in my own experience with the Bannatyne, I have been privileged to work through the lens of editors and critics such as Ritchie, Denton Fox, Priscilla Bawcutt and Hughes and Ramson. My own interpretation of these texts, while still attached to an overarching goal of providing material for pedagogical and research purposes, will be shaped by my own experience, both scholarly and personal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In accepting this, I have decided to utilise this project to contextualise the process of editing the Bannatyne further, by looking at Ritchie’s own experience, his life and work, alongside broader historical questions. It was scintillating to learn that the COCOA-encoded text of the MS, accessed via the Oxford Text Archive, is actually one of their earlier digitisations. In contacting the superlatively helpful Martin Wynne at the OTA, I have discovered a few documents pertaining to this early digitisation, and in cooperation with the DOST, have been able to find out more about A.J. Aiken’s work on this initial digitisation. The generosity of other scholars in sharing this knowledge has been exceptional, and I hope that this prosopography of the digitisation process, from Ritchie’s work onwards, will form an output from this project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, work continues on adapting the TEI files for the fourth section, and publicising the project to other academic outlets. I hope that future posts will cover things like a glossary of terms pertaining to the project, an overview of the Bannatyne’s place in Scottish history and the process that has been taking place offline, such as the inimitable Bannatyne Focus Group who have been so helpful with their input thus far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LH&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">An aspect of this project that has brought some unprecedented, and highly enjoyable, information to light is the role of one W. Tod Ritchie. This name may be familiar for those who have worked with the Bannatyne MS previously, but for those who have not, W. Tod Ritchie was the editor of the full manuscript for the Scottish Text Society in the 1920s and 1930s. In 2017, I had a remarkable encounter in a bookshop in Wigtown, Scotland’s Book Town - I found an edition of William Dunbar’s poetry that I had not previously seen. It was bound in beautiful red, and my magpie tendencies got the better of me. I was astonished to find, upon closer inspection, that this volume was inscribed as having belonged to W. Tod Ritchie himself. It was at this point that I started to really think about the nature of an editor’s relationship with their text. Holding the book in my hands, I could visualise Ritchie reading this volume, considering the choices he would go on to make in his authoritative and exhaustive edition of the Bannatyne, upon which I had so heavily relied throughout my studies.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to the Bannatyne MS Project</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/BannatyneMS/2019/06/27/welcomepost.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to the Bannatyne MS Project" /><published>2019-06-27T09:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-06-27T09:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/BannatyneMS/2019/06/27/welcomepost</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/BannatyneMS/2019/06/27/welcomepost.html">&lt;p&gt;Greetings, and welcome to the first blog entry for ‘Digitising the Bannatyne MS’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project is generously funded by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.leverhulme.ac.uk&quot;&gt;Leverhulme Trust&lt;/a&gt; and supported by the College of Arts and Science at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://artsandscience.usask.ca&quot;&gt;University of Saskatchewan&lt;/a&gt;. This project recognises that this institution is situated on Treaty 6 Territory and the homeland of the Métis. We pay our respect to the First Nations and Métis ancestors of this place and reaffirm our relationship with one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is hoped that this blog will become a working record of progress on this project. As a first entry, I wished to outline the progress that has been made thus far, and offer an idea of what will come next. Please feel free to follow us on Twitter &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/BannatyneMS&quot;&gt;@BannatyneMS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;NB: The two-year funded Postdoctoral Fellowship will focus on the digitisation of the fourth section of the manuscript. It is hoped that future funding may allow for a digitisation of the manuscript as a whole.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since arriving in Saskatoon in late January, much of my time has been spent familiarising myself with the field of Digital Humanities, as well as situating what work has been done on the Bannatyne MS thus far. I have attended a number of professional development opportunities, most notably the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dhsi.org&quot;&gt;Digital Humanities Summer Institute&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uvic.ca&quot;&gt;UVic&lt;/a&gt;, where I was fortunate enough to attend classes on ‘Conceptualising a Digital Edition’, and ‘TEI Fundamentals’. I have read widely on the current issues facing the field of Digital Humanities, and hope that this project can provide a thoughtful and informative incursion into the potential of a digital future for Older Scots studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This website represents an exciting new chapter in the project, as I move from the theoretical considerations to the practical steps in making this remarkable material available online. I would like to extend my thanks to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://programminghistorian.org&quot;&gt;Programming Historian&lt;/a&gt;, whose tutorials have helped immeasurably in establishing this website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Future blog entries will focus on short insights into the practical elements of the project, such as the utility of &lt;a href=&quot;https://tei-c.org&quot;&gt;TEI&lt;/a&gt;, the use of &lt;a href=&quot;https://iiif.io&quot;&gt;IIIF&lt;/a&gt; images, the challenges of putting material online. Alongside this, I wish to reflect on the context of the manuscript itself: who was George Bannatyne, and why should we care? What does this manuscript offer us in terms of historical and literary insight? What parallels can be drawn between Bannatyne’s editorial process and that of a digital edition?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are but some of the issues that I hope will come to light as this work progresses. Thank you for your interest in these early stages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LH&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Greetings, and welcome to the first blog entry for ‘Digitising the Bannatyne MS’.</summary></entry></feed>